SIU LUN CHAU, DPHIL

Postdoctoral Researcher at CISPA Helmholtz Center for Information Security

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research aims at building practical statistical models for **Responsible AI** along the directions of **uncertainty modelling**, **explainability**, and **preference modelling**. I believe

- Proper uncertainty modelling allows us to be honest with what the model doesn't know.
- Explainability tool will enable us to simplify and learn about the complex signals black-box models have captured.
- Incorporating preference and social values into learning can become the key to proper model alignment.

I also have research experience in kernel methods, Gaussian processes, and Causal Inference.

EDUCATION

DPhil in Statistical Science | St.Peter's College, University of Oxford

2018 – 2023

Supervisor: Prof. Dino Sejdinovic, Prof. Mihai Cucuringu, and Prof. Xiaowen Dong.

- Thesis: "Towards Trustworthy Machine Learning with Kernels"
- Published 8 papers with 6 first authored. Selected research contributions include:
 - (Bayesian kernel methods) Proposed Bayesian Conditional Mean embeddings, Causal Bayesian Conditional Mean Embeddings, and Deconditional Gaussian processes to model uncertainty while learning distributional representations in the RKHS. This resulted in 2 first authored NeurIPS publications.
 - (Explainable kernel methods) Proposed the first kernel method specific SHAP-based explanation framework RKHS-SHAP; Extended RKHS-SHAP to model non-parametric preference model and proposed PREF-SHAP. This resulted in 2 first authored NeurIPS publications.

MMATH in Mathematics and Statistics | Lady Margaret Hall, University of Oxford

= 2014 - 2018

Supervisor: Prof. Mihaela Van Der Shaar, Prof. Geoff Nicolls

 First Class Honors, ranked 2^{nd} in 4^{th} year and 1^{st} in 3^{rd} year.

WORK EXPERIENCES

Postdoctoral Researcher | CISPA Helmholtz Center for Information Security, Germany

Sep.2023 – Present

Supervisor: Dr. Krikamol Muandet

- Conducted research and supervised students on topics related to uncertainty modelling and explainability:
 - (Uncertainty) Proposed a collaborative and explainable Bayesian optimisation framework (accepted for AIS-TATS 2024); Developed an imprecise learning framework for OOD generalisation that allows the model operator to specify their generalisation strategy at test time.
 - (Explainability) Developed the first Gaussian process specific SHAP-based explanation framework (accepted for NeurIPS 2023 as spotlight); Studied the strategic behaviour of utility-maximising agents when exposed to model explanations under the causal strategic learning framework (accepted for AAAI 2024 as Oral).

Research Assistant | CISPA Helmholtz Center for Information Security, Germany

Mar.2023 – Aug.2023

• Completed my DPhil thesis while helping PhD students from the Rational Intelligence Lab with their research.

Data Scientist | Ravio (HR Tech Startup), London UK

Dec.2022 - Mar.2023

Project: Job title alignment using LLMs, Compensation modelling

- Utilised pre-trained language models to align heterogeneous job titles across companies for standardisation.
- Developed a tree-based quantile regression with monotonic constraints to model compensations.

Applied Scientist II Intern | Amazon, London UK

i Jun – Dec.2022

Project: Coherent Multi-granularity Forecasting for the Amazon Transportation Service Outbound Network

• Developed deep probabilistic coherent demand forecasting models for the EU transportation network. Solutions developed in and deployed into production-ready AWS infrastructure.

Research Intern | Max Planck Institute of Intelligent System, Tubingen Germany

iii Oct.2021 – June.2022

Project: Interface between Machine Learning and Economics (Supervised by Dr. Krikamol Muandet)

• Researched relaxing restrictive assumptions in Instrumental variable regression and examined potential non-parametric hypothesis testing framework for regression discontinuity designs. Machine Learning Consultant | Catalyst AI, Cambridge UK **Apr.2019 – Oct.2020** • Worked closely with SDEs to develop forecasting models for clients from fashion tech and agricultural companies. RESEARCH FUNDING AND AWARDS ICML 2024 Spotlight paper **M**ay.2024 AAAI 2024 Oral paper Feb.2024 Dec.2023 NeurIPS 2023 Spotlight paper Sep.2023 Helmholtz Association Postdoc funding EPSRC and MRC Studentship for DPhil in Statistics and Machine Learning **2018** Department Prize for FHS Mathematics and Statistics Part B (Top of the year) **2**017 **PUBLICATIONS** 14. Domain Generalisation via Imprecise Learning | ICML 2024 code pdf Anurag Singh, Siu Lun Chau, Shahine Bouabid, Krikamol Muandet (Spotlight paper) 13. Collaborative and Explainable Bayesian Optimisation | AISTATS 2024 code pdf Masaki Adachi, Brady Planden, David A. Howey, Krikamol Muandet, Michael A. Osborne, Siu Lun Chau 12. Causal Strategic Learning with Competitive Selection | AAAI 2024 code pdf Kiet Vo, Muneeb Aadil, Siu Lun Chau, Krikamol Muandet (Oral paper, top 2% submissions) 11. Stochastic Shapley values for Gaussian Process Models | NeurIPS 2023 pdf code Siu Lun Chau, Krikamol Muandet*, Dino Sejdinovic* (Spotlight paper, top 3% submissions) 10. Gated Domain Units for multi-source domain generasliation | TMLR 2023 pdf code Simon Föll[†], Alina Dubatovka[†], Eugen Ernst^{*}, **Siu Lun Chau**^{*}, Martin Maritsch, Patrik Okanovic, Gudrun Thäter, Joachim M. Buhmann, Felix Wortmann, Krikamol Muandet 9. Towards Trustworthy Machine Learning with Kernels | DPhil Thesis pdf Siu Lun Chau 8. Giga-scale Kernel Matrix-Vector Multiplication on GPU | NeurIPS 2022 code pdf Robert Hu, Siu Lun Chau, Dino Sejdinovic, Joan Alexis Glaunès 7. Explaining Preference with Shapley Values | NeurIPS 2022 code pdf Siu Lun Chau*, Robert Hu*, Jaime Ferrando Huertas, Dino Sejdinovic 6. RKHS-SHAP: Shapley Value for Kernel Methods | NeurIPS 2022 code pdf Siu Lun Chau, Robert Hu, Javier Gonzalez, Dino Sejdinovic 5. Spectral Ranking with Covariates | ECML PKDD 2022 code pdf Siu Lun Chau, Mihai Cucuringu, Dino Sejdinovic 4. Learning Inconsistent Preference with Gaussian Processes | AISTATS 2022 pdf Siu Lun Chau, Javier Gonzalez, Dino Sejdinovic 3. BayesIMP: Uncertainty Quantification for Causal Data Fusion | NeurIPS 2021 pdf Siu Lun Chau*, Jean Francois Ton*, Yee Whye Teh, Javier Gonzalez, Dino Sejdinovic 2. Deconditional Downscaling with Gaussian Processes | NeurIPS 2021 code pdf Siu Lun Chau*, Shahine Bouabid*, Dino Sejdinovic 1. Kernel-Based Graph Learning From Smooth Signals: A Functional Viewpoint | IEEE 2020 pdf

Xingyue Pu, Siu Lun Chau, Xiaowen Dong, Dino Sejdinovic

SELECTED INVITED TALKS

| SELECTED INVITED TALKS | |
|---|---|
| Institute of Informatics, Ludwig-Maximilians-Universität München (LMU) | i Mar.2024 |
| Australian Data Science Network 2023 | Dec.2023 |
| School of Computing, Australian National University | Nov.2023 |
| Data 61, CSIRO, Melbourne | Nov.2023 |
| School of Computing and Information Systems, University of Melbourne | ■ Nov.2023 |
| Australian Institute for Machine Learning, University of Adelaide | Nov.2023 |
| The Department Management, Technology, and Economics, ETH Zurich | Sep.2023 |
| ETH AI Center | E Sep.2023 |
| Oxford-Man Institute, University of Oxford | Sep.2023 |
| CISPA – Helmholtz Center for Information Security | i Feb.2023 |
| ELISE Theory Workshop on ML Fundamentals, EURECOM | Sep.2022 |
| S-DCE Alan Turing Institute seminar | ä Jun.2022 |
| Gatsby Unit, University College London | m May.2022 |
| UCL SML group | i Feb.2022 |
| Imperial & Oxford StatML seminar | i Feb.2022 |
| Max Planck Institute for Intelligent Systems | Cct.2021 |
| Warwick ML Group, University of Warwick | ä Jun.2021 |
| SUPERVISION \ MENTORSHIP EXPERIENCE | |
| PhD Students | |
| Anurag Singh, Kiet Vo (University of Saarland) | Saarbrucken, Germany |
| Mentoring junior PhD students in our group | Mar.2023 - Present |
| Masters Students | |
| Swathi Suhas (University of Saarland) Project: "Explainable Machine Learning" | Saarbrucken, Germany Mar.2024 - Present |
| Oscar Yung (University of Oxford) Thesis: "Two Sample Testing for Regression Discontinuity Design" | Oxford, United Kingdom Feb.2022 - May.2022 |
| Samuel Weinman (University of Oxford) | Oxford, United Kingdom |
| THESIS: "Analysis of Price-Volume Interplay in Financial Markets via Machine Learning" | May.2020 - Aug.2020 |
| Undergraduate Students | |
| Mohammad Mehdi Mojarradi, Jihong Lee (Williams College) Williams-Exeter Exchange Program at Oxford University | Oxford, United Kingdom Mar.2021 - Nov.2021 |
| William Conyers, Daniel Park (Williams College) | Oxford, United Kingdom |
| Williams-Exeter Exchange Program at Oxford University | Jan.2020 - Mar.2020 |
| TEACHING | |
| University of Oxford | |
| Tutor, A12 Simulation and Statistical Programming Tutor, SB1.1 Applied Statistics | 2020 2020 |
| Tutor, SB1.2 Computational Statistics | 2020 |
| Tutor, SB2.2 Statistical Machine Learning | 2021 |
| Teaching Assistant, SB2.1 Foundations of Statistical Inference | 2019 |